Nishant Subramani - Aspiring Machine Learning Researcher

nishant.subramani23@gmail.com

http://github.com/hatat5

https://hatat5.github.io

Objective

I am a PhD Student in Computer Science in the Courant Institute at New York University working on machine learning and deep learning advised by Kyunghyun Cho and Sam Bowman. Currently I am working multi-task learning, neural machine translation, importance-sampling for neural language modeling, and causality.

• Research Interests: Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Multi-Task Learning, Causality, Interventional and Counterfactual Reasoning.

Education

New York University

New York, NY

PhD Computer Science focusing on Machine Learning

Sept 2017 - Present

 $\circ\,$ Advisors: Kyunghyun Cho and Sam Bowman

Northwestern University

Evanston, IL

B.A./M.S. Statistics/Computer Science; **Stat GPA:** 3.963/4.000; **MS GPA:** 4.000/4.000 Sept 2013 – June 2017

- Graduate Courses: Deep Learning, Machine Learning Foundations, Probabilistic Graphical Models, Data Mining, Adv Topics in ML, Statistical Pattern Recognition, Computational Learning Theory, Adv Topics in Bayesian Stats
- Undergrad Courses: Machine Learning, Intro to AI, Regression Analysis, Statistical Computing, Statistical Theory & Methodology I-III, Theory of Computation, Biochemistry, Cell and Molecular Biology

Publications

- 1. Subramani, Nishant, and Doug Downey. "PAG2ADMG: A Novel Methodology to Enumerate Causal Graph Structures" In 31st AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence. 2017. **Student Abstract**
- 2. Subramani, Nishant. "Identifying the Best Predictors of Unmet Health Care Needs in Children with DBD." Northwestern Undergraduate Research Journal (2015).

Research Experience

PhD Researcher in Machine Learning

New York University

PIs: Kyunghyun Cho and Sam Bowman

September 2017 – Present

- **Project 1: Working on natural language generation for machine translation, summarization, and image captioning. Deep Learning, Neural Machine Translation (NMT), LSTMs, Attention
- **Project 2: Improving pag2admg algorithm into a more efficient method to generate all Markov equivalent acyclic directed mixed graphs. Causality, Ancestral Graphs, Acyclic Directed Mixed Graphs, Markov Equivalence

Deep Learning Research Intern

Salesforce (Metamind Group)

PI: Richard Socher

March 2017 – August 2017

• **Project:** Worked on multitask learning, specifically trying to build a single system that could perform well on a myriad of NLP tasks *Deep Learning*, *MultiTask Learning*, *BiLSTMs*, *NLP*, *Meta-learning*

Research Assistant in Deep Learning & NLP

Northwestern University

PI: Doug Downey

July 2014 - March 2015; March 2016 - June 2017

- Statistics Bachelor's Thesis (Accepted to ICML 2018 Workshop on Causality): Improving my pag2admg developed at ETH Zurich into a method that generates all Markov equivalent acyclic directed mixed graphs (not necessary just ancestral) from a PAG. Causality, Ancestral Graphs, Mixed Graphs, Markov Equivalence
- Master's Thesis: Developing various methodologies to identify deep net hyperparameter settings more efficiently using active learning and sampling. Deep Learning, Hyperparameters, LSTMs, ConvNets, Active Learning
- **Project 3**: Developing various ensembling methodologies to improve state-of-the-art language model performance on the Penn Tree Bank dataset. *Deep Learning, Recurrent Neural Nets (RNNs), XGBoost*
- Project 4: Developing alternative dropout methodologies to increase variance of models from epoch to epoch to improve deep neural network performance on a variety of tasks. Deep Learning, Dropout, RNNs, ConvNets
- **Project 5**: Developed methods to input pre-existing analogical knowledge to improve word-embeddings in Google's word2vec models. *Neural Networks, Active Learning*
- Project 6** (Plan to Submit to EMNLP 2018 Workshop on Analyzing NNs for NLP): Developing methods
 to utilize importance sampling to help stochastic gradient descent convergence for neural sentence-level language modeling.
 Neural Networks, Importance Sampling, LSTMs, SGD

Research Assistant in Biomedical Informatics

Stanford University

PI: Olivier Gevaert

Jun 2015 - Jan 2016

• Project 1: Used predictive models to identify a genetic basis for cellularity in brain cancer patients using gene expression and cellular pathology data. Bayesian Networks, Structure Learning, Hierarchical Clustering

^{** -} indicates currently working on

Research Assistant in Biomedical Informatics

Feinberg School of Medicine

PI: Yuan Luo

Jan 2016 – March 2016

• **Project**: Predicted ICU 30-day readmission rates from a multivariate panel of physiological measurements using Subgraph Augmented Non-Negative Matrix Factorization (SANMF). *Non-Negative Matrix Factorization, Frequent Subgraph Mining*

Master's Semester Project Student in Systems Biology

ETH Zurich

PI: Manfred Claassen

Sept 2015 - Jan 2016

o **Project**: Developed a methodology (*The Boundary Searcher*) to efficiently calculate the r-convex hull of a point cloud in high dimensions. *R-Convex Hull, Random Walk*

Master's Semester Project Student in Statistics

ETH Zurich

PI: Marloes Maathuis

Sept 2015 - Jan 2016

• **Project**: Developed a novel methodology to transform a given partial ancestral graph (PAG) to the set of all ancestral acyclic directed mixed graphs that belong in the Markov equivalence class that the PAG encodes. *Causality, Ancestral Graphs, Directed Graphs, Mixed Graphs*

Teaching Experience

Teaching Assistant for Natural Language Understanding (Grad Course)

DSGA-1012

New York University Jan 2018 – May 2018

Jan 2017 - Mar 2017

- o Developed homework assignments and exercises throughout the course.
- Helped advise research projects completed by students in the course that involved deep learning applied to language.

Teaching Assistant for Adv Topics in ML (Grad Seminar)

Northwestern University

EECS 395/495

- o Course Topic: Statistical Language Modeling focusing on Deep Learning.
- o Constructed seminar reading list, helping other students understand seminal deep NLP papers.

Teaching Assistant for Probabilistic Graphical Models (Grad Course) EECS 474

Northwestern University

Sept 2016 - Dec 2016

- o Helped to design course materials and structure.
- o Developed and graded assignments; held office hours.

Teaching Assistant for Mathematical Foundations of CS

Northwestern University

EECS 212

Sept 2016 – Dec 2016

o Helped to develop and grade assignments and exams; held office hours.

Teaching Assistant for Machine Learning

Northwestern University

EECS 349

Feb 2016 – June 2016

- Devised methodology for and built a mechanical TA which uses the Vancouver crowd sourcing algorithm.
- $\circ~$ Helped to design tree search and decision tree assignments, graded assignments, and held office hours.

Teaching Assistant for Computing Applications I & II

Northwestern University

ISP 101-1 & 101-2

Sept 2014 – March 2015

- \circ Co-taught course with three other teaching assistants.
- $\circ~$ Wrote exam questions and assignments covering python and R basics.

Other Experience

Deep Learning Consultant

Talkspace

Hiring Manager: Bonnie Ray

November 2017 – August 2018

- Taught Talkspace's Data Science team about deep learning fundamentals and how to implement deep neural network models for text.
- \circ Helped advise building and training deep neural network models for domain-specific problems with text.

Skills

- Proficient Languages/Packages: Python, R, PyTorch
- Machine Learning Algorithms: Deep Nets (RNNs, LSTMs, CNNs), Bayesian Networks, SVMs, Logistic Regression, Decision Trees, Random Forests
- Other Computational Methods: AdaBoost, Clustering (K-means, Hierarchical), Map-Reduce

Research Presentations

• PAG2ADMG. ICML 2018, Stockholm, Sweden. Causal ML Workshop. Poster.

July 2018

• PAG2ADMG. AAAI 2017, San Francisco, CA. Student Abstract Spotlight Talk.

February 2017

• PAG2ADMG. AAAI 2017, San Francisco, CA. Student Abstract Poster.

February 2017

• Pag2Admg. Undergraduate Research Expo, Northwestern University. Poster.	June 2016
• The Boundary Searcher. EECS Poster Fair, Northwestern University. Poster.	Apr 2016
• Predicting Unmet Health Care Needs in Children with DBD Undergraduate Research Expo, Northwestern University. Poster.	June 2015
• Predicting Unmet Health Care Needs in Children with DBD EECS Poster Fair, Northwestern University. Poster.	Mar 2015
• How Evil are Turnovers? Undergraduate Research Expo, Northwestern University. Talk.	June 2014
• How Evil are Turnovers? Computational Statistics Conference, Northwestern University. Poster.	Apr 2014

Professional Service

Delegate Reviewer for NIPS 2017
 Delegate Reviewer for ICCV 2017
 May 2017

Awards & Honors

• Henry M. MacCracken Graduate Fellowship (5 Year Fully Funded PhD Studies) September 2017 - August • \$500 Conference Travel Grant from Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences June 2018 • \$500 Conference Travel Grant from Weinberg College of Arts & Sciences January 2017 • \$500 Conference Travel Grant from Undergraduate Research Northwestern University January 2017 • Charles A & Ruby E Howell Endowed Scholarship December 2014 - June 2017 • Academic Dean's List September 2014 - June 2016 • Intel Science Talent Search (ISTS) Outstanding Written Report Award March 2013 • National AP Scholar August 2012

Students Advised

Michael Chen - B.S. Student in Computer Science, Northwestern University
 Gautam Srinivasan - M.S. Student in Computer Science, New York University
 August 2018 - Present